YMCA ARMED SERVICES DEPARTMENT:
University of Minnesota Libraries
World War I-related records.
1910-1970
(bulk 1917-1921).
University of Minnesota. Kautz Family YMCA Archives. [ymca]
National Board of the Young Men's Christian Associations. Armed Services Dept.
Y.USA.4-1
Minutes, correspondence, publicity bulletins, training manuals, reports, newspapers, and other records of major YMCA administrative bodies which provided services to the military forces in the United States and abroad during World War I..
59.2 cu. ft. (144 boxes).
HISTORY OF YMCA ARMED SERVICES WORK IN WORLD WAR I
The United States entered World War I on 6 April 1917. On that same day, John Mott, General Secretary of the International Committee of North American YMCAs, informed President Wilson that the YMCA would help provide services for the military forces. Less than a week later, the International Committee appointed the National War Work Council to coordinate this work. William S. Sloane, a New York furniture merchant and for sixteen years chairman of the YMCA's Army and Navy Committee, was designated as the new organization's chairman, and Mott as its chief executive officer. A specific military function was assigned to the YMCA. Its duty was to assist in maintaining and promoting morale and welfare. It had been proved in the Spanish American War and on the Mexican border that YMCA service made better fighters.
The YMCA conducted its war work with soldiers in training camps and troop trains in the United States as well as in Europe, providing recreation, library services, bible study, and religious services. In France the YMCA agreed to run the Post Exchange for the army, and thus sold candy, cigarettes, and other personal items to the soldiers. War work went under several names, including Red Triangle work and AEF work (AEF stood for American Expeditionary Forces, which referred to the American army in France). The National War Work Council also financed similar work for French soldiers under the name "Foyer du Soldat." Additional work was carried out in Italy, Greece, Russia, and a number of other countries. The YMCA also provided services to prisoners of war in a number of countries.
In the course of staffing its assigned operations and the other activities which fell to its lot along the way, the YMCA recruited a grand total of 25,926 workers who, about equally divided between home and overseas assignments, served under the Red Triangle. These workers were selected from approximately 2000,000 applications. Women workers comprised about 20 percent of the total, twice as many of whom served overseas as served on the home front.
In November 1918, the YMCA conducted a fundraising campaign in conjunction with six other welfare organizations: The YWCA, the Jewish Welfare Board, the Knights of Columbus, the Salvation Army, the American Library Association, and War Camp Community Service. The effort, known as the United War Campaign, raised $192 million.
Immediately after the war, the YMCA followed American occupying forces into Germany, working primarily out of the city of Koblenz. This was referred to as AFG work (i.e. American Forces in Germany). Due to unsettled conditions in the war area and the fact that a peace treaty had not yet been signed, work among young men of Allied countries and among prisoners of war was still continuing. In the United States, a postwar program of special significance was an extensive educational service, financed by war work funds, which enabled ex-servicemen to complete studies interrupted by the war or to secure further preparation for re-entry into civilian life.
Although it received much praise for its work, after the war the YMCA was the target of numerous complaints from soldiers. The allegations mostly related to the YMCA's operation of canteens, and involved accusations that it had sold items at inflated prices or items which were to be distributed free. There were a number of official investigations into the YMCA's wartime conduct, for the most part exonerating the Y.
Much of the historical information in this summary was taken from Serving the U.S. Armed Forces, 1861-1986: The Story of the YMCA's Ministry to Military Personnel for 125 Years, by Richard C. Lancaster; and Summary of World War Work of the American YMCA, a 1920 report published by the International Committee of the YMCA.
SCOPE AND CONTENTS OF THE COLLECTION
The records include minutes and related materials from major administrative bodies, primarily the National War Work Council and its subcommittees: the executive committee, the finance committee, the committee of eleven, the committee of fourteen, the religious work bureau committee, the overseas committee, and the committee of nine. Also included are press releases, publicity bulletins, and fundraising materials; training pamphlets for war workers; blueprints of buildings for war work; and correspondence and reports relating to work in army camps. There are also reports and correspondence relating the the dissolution of the War Work Council.
A major portion of the records consists of materials relating to the United War Work Campaign, a joint campaign of seven American welfare organizations, including the YMCA. These records include minutes, bylaws, and agreements; correspondence, reports, and minutes of the committee of eleven; correspondence of John Mott relating to the campaign; financial statements and budget materials; press releases, bulletins, and promotional publications; state and local fundraising materials; and staff lists. There are also reports and publications of the other organizations which participated in the Campaign, including the American Library Association, the Jewish Welfare Board, the the Salvation Army.
Materials relating to various program departments include publications of the Army Educational Commission; reports and publications of educational work in France; and reports and publications concerning entertainment, transportation, work by women, and work in the area of physical fitness and recreation (the latter includes publications on the Inter-Allied Games held in Paris in 1919).
Records relating to the AEF YMCA are also included in the collection and consist of publications, correspondence, and minutes relating to work with American soldiers in France; AFG (American Forces in Germany) materials, including pamphlets for soldiers and reports concerning work with the occupying forces; and leave area publications relating to recreational and site-seeing opportunities in France and Germany.
A variety of materials contain personal reminiscences of YMCA work, including narrative manuscripts, personal journals, interviews of secretaries, testimonials of soldiers, and a historical statement. The collection also includes three sets of personnel records for war workers: a punch card file, a contract file, and a statements of returning secretaries. These provide names, addresses, and information on YMCA war work service.
Prisoner of war work is documented by administrative correspondence, budget materials, reports, news clippings, and publications for prisoners. There is also a pictorial publication describing work with eastern European prisoners.
A number of YMCA-sponsored newspapers for soldiers are included in these records. The most prominent of these is the Red Triangle Bulletin, reporting on work in France. Trench and Camp, a joint project between the YMCA and various U.S. newspapers, was distributed in military camps in the United States.
Non-YMCA materials relating to YMCA war work and the war in general include government reports and publications on matters such as selective service, training camps, and regulations. There are also some reports to the English Parliament on prisoner-of-war work.
There is voluminous material concerning the post-war investigations of the YMCA's work. These include the eleven volume "YMCA Answer to the Inspector General" and the five volume "Letter from E. C. Carter to William Sloane Supplementing YMCA Answer to the Inspector General'; Answers to Criticisms"; "Report on the Investigation of the YMCA"; and articles and news clippings.
Also included in the collection are materials relating to the military build-up on the Mexican border in 1916. The YMCA followed the soldiers and did war work there. These materials include promotional publications, news clippings, press materials, Border Work (another YMCA-sponsored newspaper for soldiers), blueprint maps, and a report on the work.
ADMINISTRATIVE INFORMATION
DETAILED DESCRIPTION OF THE COLLECTION
The following section contains a detailed list of the materials in the collection. To request materials, please note the corresponding box number.
- National War Work Council, minutes and documents, 1917-1921.; 6 folders. (Box 1)
- National War Work Council, minutes and documents, 1924-1927. (Box 1)
- Trustees of the War Fund of the YMCA, minutes, 1920-1927. (Box 1)
- Executive Committee of National War Work Council, minutes, 1917-1921.; 8 folders. (Box 1)
- National War Work Council, negotiations with Armed Forces, 1919. (Box 1)
- Executive Committee of National War Work Council, minutes, 1917-1920.; 5 folders. (Box 2)
- Executive Committee of National War Work Council, minutes (duplicates), 1917-1920.; 11 folders. (Box 2)
- National War Work Council, minutes (duplicates), 1917-1920. (Box 2)
- Finance Committee of the National War Work Council, minutes, 1917-1920.; 5 folders. (Box 3)
- Joint Meeting of the Executive and Financial Committees of the National War Work Council, minutes, 1919-1920. (Box 3)
- Committee of Eleven, minutes, 1918-1921.; 6 folders. (Box 3)
- Committee of Fourteen, minutes, 1918-1920. (Box 3)
- Committee on Allied Armies and Prisoners of War, minutes, 1918-1922.; 3 folders. (Box 3)
- Overseas Committee, minutes, 1923-1924. (Box 3)
- Army Educational Commission, 1919. (Box 4)
- Committee of Nine, minutes, 1918. (Box 4)
- National War Work Council, recommendations from overseas, 1918. (Box 4)
- National War Work Council, directories, 1917-1918. (Box 4)
- National War Work Council, campaign organization and promotion details, 1917. (Box 4)
- National War Work Council, fundraising materials, 1917.; 5 folders. (Box 4)
- National War Work Council, financial statements and audits, 1918-1927.; 2 folders. (Box 4)
- National War Work Council, publicity bulletins, 1917.; 2 folders. (Box 4)
- National War Work Council, Camp Bulletin, 1917-1919.; 3 folders. (Box 4)
- National War Work Council, press releases, 1917.; 14 folders. (Box 5)
- National War Work Council, press releases, 1917.; 9 folders. (Box 6)
- National War Work Council, recruiting materials for war work, 1918. (Box 6)
- National War Work Council, training program report, 1919. (Box 6)
- National War Work Council, Manual for Camp Work, 1917-1918. (Box 6)
- National War Work Council, The Uniform of Honor and Elementary Textbook for YMCA Secretaries in Military Obedience, Courtesy, Bearing and Litter Drill, 1918. (Box 6)
- Religious Work Bureau, miscellaneous, 1917-1919.; 2 folders. (Box 6)
- Religious Work Bureau, minutes, 1917-1919.; 4 folders. (Box 7)
- Religious Work Bureau, Religious Work Program pamphlet, 1918. (Box 7)
- National War Work Council, war personnel board, directories, 1917-1918.; 12 folders. (Box 7)
- War Personnel Board, roster, 1918. (Box 7)
- War Personnel Board, training materials, 1918. (Box 7)
- War Personnel Board, enlistment materials, 1917-1918. (Box 7)
- War Personnel Board, blank forms, 1918. (Box 7)
- War Work Training School, materials, 1917-1918.; 7 folders. (Box 8)
- National War Work Council-Southeast, 1917-1918.; 5 folders. (Box 8)
- National War Work Council-Southern, 1917-1918.; 8 folders. (Box 8)
- National War Work Council, demobilization, 1918-1919.; 8 folders. (Box 9)
- National War Work Council, reports, 1917-1927.; 12 folders. (Box 9)
- National War Work Council, trustees of war work fund, 1914-1919, 1940, 1943. (Box 9)
- National War Work Council, Bureau of Construction, 1917-1921.; 3 folders. (Box 10)
- National War Work Council, correspondence and statements re: YMCA work in Army posts and camps, 1918-1920.; 2 folders. (Box 10)
- National War Work Council, Committee on War Industries, 1917-1919.; 4 folders. (Box 10)
- National War Work Council, Joint Committee of 10, 1920. (Box 10)
- National War Work Council, Committee of 14, 1915-1918. (Box 10)
- National War Work Council, Chicago Plan, 1919-1920. (Box 10)
- National War Work Council, fund reports and correspondence, 1919-1927.; 3 folders. (Box 11)
- National War Work Council, budgets, 1918-1919. (Box 11)
- National War Work Council, Supreme Court accounting, correspondence and reports, 1922-1933.; 4 folders. (Box 11)
- National War Work Council, dissolution reports, 1917-1946.; 3 folders. (Box 11)
- National War Work Council, trustee reports, 1919-1928.; 2 folders. (Box 11)
- National War Work Council, Liquidation Committee, 1921-1924.; 2 folders. (Box 11)
- Various wartime organizations and YMCA committees, minutes, 1917-1919. (Box 12)
- United War Work Campaign, general committee, minutes, 1918. (Box 12)
- United War Work Campaign Executive Committee, reports and minutes, 1918. (Box 12)
- United War Work Campaign, budget sub-committee, 1918-1919. (Box 12)
- United War Work Campaign, reports and minutes, 1918. (Box 12)
- United War Work Campaign, certificate of incorporation, 1918. (Box 12)
- United War Work Campaign, minutes of general committee and national cabinet, index, 1918. (Box 12)
- United War Work Campaign Joint Executive Committee, minutes, 1918. (Box 12)
- United War Work Campaign, National Cabinet, minutes, 1918.; 2 folders. (Box 12)
- United War Work Campaign, Committee of Eleven, correspondence and reports, 1917-1919. (Box 12)
- United War Work Campaign, Committee of Eleven, minutes and correspondence, 1918-1919. (Box 12)
- United War Work Campaign, Committee of Eleven, minutes and correspondence, 1920. (Box 12)
- United War Work Campaign, Committee of Eleven, minutes, 1920-1921. (Box 12)
- United War Work Campaign, J. Mott, correspondence, 1918-1919. (Box 12)
- United War Work Campaign, Committee of Three, reports, 1919. (Box 12)
- Trustees of the War Fund, minutes, 1920-1927. (Box 12)
- National War Work Council, financial reports, 1918-1928. (Box 12)
- United War Work Campaign, Finance Committee, minutes, 1918-1921.; 4 folders. (Box 13)
- United War Work Campaign, circular letters and telegrams, 1918. (Box 13)
- United War Work Campaign, endorsement correspondence, 1918. (Box 13)
- United War Work Campaign, correspondence regarding protests against campaign, 1918. (Box 13)
- United War Work Campaign, financial statements, 1918-1921. (Box 13)
- United War Work Campaign, quota statements, 1918. (Box 13)
- United War Work Campaign, budget materials, 1917-1919. (Box 13)
- United War Work Campaign, final audit, 1928-1930. (Box 13)
- United War Work Campaign, correspondence regarding 1933 disbursement (Box 13)
- United War Work Campaign, materials relating to merger negotiations of campaigns, 1918.; 2 folders (Box 13)
- United War Work Campaign, campaign plan book, 1918. (Box 13)
- United War Work Campaign, bulletins, 1918. (Box 13)
- United War Work Campaign, promotional publications, 1917-1918.; 2 folders. (Box 13)
- United War Work Campaign, pledge cards, 1918. (Box 14)
- United War Work Campaign, staff and committee lists, circa 1918.; 4 folders. (Box 14)
- United War Work Campaign, press releases, 1918.; 2 folders. (Box 14)
- United War Work Campaign, miscellaneous press materials, circa 1917-1920.; 2 folders. (Box 14)
- United War Work Campaign, cartoon contest materials, 1918. (Box 14)
- United War Work Campaign, publications and clippings, circa 1918.; 6 folders. (Box 14)
- United War Work Campaign, publications and clippings, circa 1918.; 10 folders. (Box 15)
- New York Herald articles on YMCA in WW I, 1917-1919.; 6 folders. (Box 15)
- War work clippings, California, Oregon and Washington, 1919.; 3 folders. (Box 16)
- War work clippings from New England states, 1918.; 5 folders. (Box 16)
- News clippings on war work, 1916-1918.; 2 folders. (Box 16)
- United War Work Campaign, promotional publications, 1918-1921.; 3 folders. (Box 16)
- United War Work Campaign, miscellaneous publications, 1918-1919. (Box 16)
- United War Work Campaign, blank forms, circa 1918.; 2 folders. (Box 16)
- United War Work Campaign, reports and correspondence, 1917. (Box 17)
- United War Work Campaign, financial lists, 1917.; 2 folders. (Box 17)
- United War Work Campaign, financial reports, 1917-1918.; 3 folders. (Box 17)
- United War Work Campaign, publicity, 1917.; 2 folders. (Box 17)
- United War Work Campaign, Victory Boys, publications and reports, 1917-1918.; 5 folders. (Box 18)
- United War Work Campaign, foreign countries, 1917-1918.; 3 folders. (Box 18)
- United War Work Campaign, Brazil, 1918-1919. (Box 18)
- United War Work Campaign, China, 1918-1919. (Box 18)
- United War Work Campaign, Cuba, 1918. (Box 18)
- United War Work Campaign, Mexico, 1918. (Box 18)
- United War Work Campaign, Puerto Rico, 1918. (Box 18)
- United War Work Campaign, Hawaiian islands, 1918. (Box 18)
- United War Work Campaign, Bel Air, MD claim, 1938-1939.; 2 folders. (Box 18)
- Hopkins, World War I notes, circa 1950. (Box 18)
- United War Work Campaign, Victory Boys, miscellaneous materials, 1917-1918.; 15 folders. (Box 19)
- United War Work Campaign, miscellaneous state and local fundraising pamphlets, circa 1917-1919.; 6 folders. (Box 20)
- United War Work Campaign, Indiana State War Work, reports, 1919-1920. (Box 20)
- United War Work Campaign, Puerto Rico, correspondence and reports, circa 1918.; 3 folders. (Box 20)
- United War Work Campaign, miscellaneous, circa 1918. (Box 20)
- Education Bureau, reports and publications, circa 1914-1919.; 3 folders. (Box 20)
- Education Bureau, publications and reports, circa 1914-1919.; 8 folders. (Box 21)
- Crises in American History, discussion outline, 1918. (Box 21)
- Education Commission, publications, 1918.; 7 folders. (Box 21)
- Report on morale, 1919. (Box 21)
- Materials found with report on morale, circa 1917-1919. (Box 21)
- Transportation Bureau, records, 1918-1920.; 2 folders. (Box 21)
- Transportation Bureau, publications, circa 1918. (Box 21)
- Education Department, Extension Division, 1919.; 2 folders. (Box 22)
- Education Department, Activities Committee, 1918-1919.; 2 folders. (Box 22)
- Education Department, Community Motion Picture Bureau, 1919. (Box 22)
- Publicity policy, 1917. (Box 22)
- Army and Navy Department, 1920-1926. (Box 22)
- Educational Commission, materials, 1918-1919.; 13 folders. (Box 22)
- Education Commission, materials, 1918-1926.; 4 folders. (Box 23)
- Legal Department, interview with Reginald Robbins, 1920. (Box 23)
- Legal Department, interview with Franklin Edmonds, 1920. (Box 23)
- War Historical Bureau, interview with Elwood Brown, 1920.; 2 folders. (Box 23)
- War Historical Bureau, interview with George Fisher, 1920. (Box 23)
- Athletic Bulletin, 1920-1921.; 2 folders. (Box 23)
- Far Eastern Athletic Association, The World at Play-A Program of Practical Athletics for the Millions, 1913-1920. (Box 23)
- Recreation publications, circa 1917-1918.; 4 folders. (Box 23)
- Occasional Letters, undated. (Box 24)
- Recreation publications, circa 1917-1919.; 4 folders. (Box 24)
- Physical education publications, circa 1918-1921.; 5 folders. (Box 24)
- Interview with John H. McCuroy, 1920. (Box 24)
- Athletic Department, report, 1918. (Box 24)
- Physical Education, instructions to the field, Occasional Letters, 1919. (Box 24)
- Inter-Allied Games, publications, 1919.; 4 folders. (Box 24)
- An Army of Athletes: Playing Fields, Battlefields and the American Military Sporting Experience, 1890-1920, 1995. (Box 24)
- Inter-Allied Games, miscellaneous, 1919. (Box 24)
- Inter-Allied Games, Victory Games, by James Diamond, 1988. (Box 24)
- World War I entertainment clippings, 1919-1921.; 3 volumes. (Box 25)
- Entertainment articles and programs, 1918-1920. (Box 25)
- World War I entertainment clippings, 1919-1921.; 4 volumes. (Box 26)
- Entertainment report, Brest Region, 1919.; 3 folders. (Box 27)
- Entertainment reports and articles, 1918-1919.; 2 folders. (Box 27)
- Entertainment articles and programs, 1918-1920.; 3 folders. (Box 27)
- Loose material found in entertainment clippings scrapbook, 1919-1921. (Box 27)
- War Industries, materials, 1918-1919.; 3 folders. (Box 27)
- War Industries, Pacific Coast section, 1918-1919. (Box 27)
- AEF-YMCA, budget, 1918.; 2 folders. (Box 28)
- Chief Secretary's file, volume A, 1917-1919.; 11 folders. (Box 28)
- Chief Secretary's file, volume B, 1917-1919.; 6 folders. (Box 28)
- Chief Secretary's file, volume C, 1917-1919.; 5 folders. (Box 29)
- Chief Secretary's file, volume D, 1917-1919.; 8 folders. (Box 29)
- Chief Secretary's file, volume E, 1917-1919.; 6 folders. (Box 30)
- Chief Secretary's file, volume F, 1917-1919.; 8 folders. (Box 30)
- Chief Secretary's file, volume G, 1917-1919.; 4 folders. (Box 31)
- Chief Secretary's files, 1917-1919.; 5 folders. (Box 31)
- AEF-YMCA, miscellaneous committee minutes, 1917-1919.; 6 folders. (Box 32)
- AEF-YMCA, miscellaneous publications, 1918-1919.; 3 folders. (Box 32)
- AEF-YMCA Chief Secretary's file, miscellaneous publications, 1917-1919.; 5 folders. (Box 32)
- AEF-YMCA, miscellaneous publications, 1918-1919.; 4 folders. (Box 33)
- AEF-YMCA, athletic bulletins, 1918-1919.; 5 folders. (Box 33)
- AEF-YMCA, Religious Department, publications, 1918-1919.; 6 folders. (Box 33)
- AEF-YMCA, Religious Department, publications, 1918-1919.; 3 folders. (Box 34)
- AEF-YMCA, Construction Department, blueprints, 1918-1919.; 11 folders. (Box 34)
- AEF-YMCA, Education Department, Art Training Center report, 1919.; 2 folders. (Box 35)
- AEF-YMCA, Education Department, publications, 1919.; 3 folders. (Box 35)
- AEF Chief Secretary's file, official bulletins, 1917-1919.; 3 folders. (Box 36)
- Bulletins relating to YMCA, 1919.; 6 folders. (Box 36)
- Answers to criticisms of YMCA publicity, circa 1919.; 5 folders. (Box 36)
- AEF Finance Committee, minutes, 1918-1919.; 12 folders. (Box 37)
- AEF Finance Committee-France, minutes, 1919-1920.; 3 folders. (Box 37)
- Outline of headquarters organization, circa 1918. (Box 37)
- Handbook of American YMCA, 1918.; 2 folders. (Box 37)
- Overseas Committee, 1918-1919.; 2 folders. (Box 38)
- Negotiations between the YMCA and the Army/Navy, 1917-1919.; 4 folders. (Box 38)
- Executive Committee, minutes, 1918-1919.; 2 folders. (Box 38)
- Social hygiene pamphlets, 1916-1919.; 11 folders. (Box 38)
- Social hygiene, interview, 1920. (Box 38)
- YMCA postcards and stationary, circa 1918. (Box 38)
- W. L. Denlinger files, YMCA warehouse in Gievres, 1918-1922. (Box 38)
- AEF in London, printed material, 1918-1920.; 3 folders. (Box 39)
- AEF in London, Washington Inn visitors book, 1918. (Box 39)
- AEF in London, materials found with Washington Inn visitors book, 1918. (Box 39)
- AEF-YMCA, accounting materials, 1918.; 5 folders. (Box 39)
- AEF in Great Britain, 1918-1920.; 3 folders. (Box 39)
- AEF-YMCA Statement of Work in the United Kingdom for the American Army, 1919.; 3 folders. (Box 39)
- England, port work, 1920. (Box 39)
- Service of American YMCA to the Italian Army, circa 1918.; 4 folders. (Box 40)
- Italian army materials, 1918-1919.; 11 folders. (Box 40)
- War Historical Bureau, interview with Charles D. Hurrey, 1920. (Box 40)
- War Historical Bureau, interview with Clarence E. Beasley, 1920. (Box 40)
- War Historical Bureau, interview with Guy Potter Benson, 1920. (Box 40)
- War Historical Bureau, interview with J. Campbell Brandon, 1919. (Box 40)
- War Historical Bureau, interview with Carl Cate, 1920. (Box 40)
- War Historical Bureau, interview with Myron Clark, 1920. (Box 40)
- War Historical Bureau, interview with W. G. Coxhead, 1919. (Box 40)